I have a lot of the invocation of our chief, but Chris General, Heavenly Father, we're thankful for you and we're thankful for this community and the blessing it is for so many ways to ask that you leave the meeting tonight that the discussion that's had is honest and respectful and productive and give our council members wisdom as they make decisions for the community that affect us as all in your name we pray.
Congratulations to the flag of the United States of America and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation under God in a visible liberty and justice for our.
For the people of the world, a personal.
Parents.
5.
Plains list.
Most of the proof.
meeting.
Motion approved.
Stoneball.
Hi.
Barnes.
Jones.
Estep.
Parker.
Hey, you know, Stratten Edmonds and Palmer Claim for PIN School of G.R.D.A.
Realizing Associated Complaint.
We're seeing proceeding in the amount of $945 dollars.
I guess we're getting this.
That he said $9 or $4 or $5 or we spend.
If this is approved in the $104,000, $8,000, $8,000, $8,000, $8,000, $8,000.
As you all are.
I'm listening.
Thank you.
Jones.
Don't pull.
Hi.
Barnes.
Estep.
Parker.
Hi.
Not in discussion.
I'm sorry to waste management alternatives.
The valuation.
Percented by burns.
And make Donald.
Julie Davis.
Tyler Pomp.
So we have.
We actually have a Laura here today.
Julie.
Well, in the high-cester day in Kansas City.
Oh.
Thanks.
You broke the tickets.
Hi.
I'm happy to be here.
Okay.
It's started.
All right.
So more of us are going to run in Act 4 on the 15 years.
And we're going to fire my own generic team.
So we focus on.
Solidly, it's form of our environmental system.
There's more of this region.
I hope that the Oklahoma Department will fire my quality on the top 3 of YouTube.
Contrast.
But we recently wrapped up a study for the solid waste alternatives.
We're looking at opportunities for future facility.
I'm doing this.
in one of my installs over here?
It might be turned off.
All right.
Thank you.
I'll do a quick overview of the process
and you have your project overview.
We'll go over a new Transversation Serial Analysis.
I mean, when we install scenario analysis, we do two different versions of that,
and then I'll present our key findings and recommendations for next steps.
So you're current Transversation.
You take in about 20,000 tons per year from the city,
the city has residential and commercial customers,
additional residents in the city.
The facility as well as external customers.
It's reached the end of its useful life.
So it's very common facilities are used for 30 years.
And significant improvement to continue operations.
The facility also was on a former incinerator site,
so it wasn't originally designed to be a Transversation facility.
We've seen contracts with a landfill.
70 miles away for the actual disposal.
So that's for public and limaar.
And the waste is combined at the Transversation and then
transport it to the landfill in limaar.
That is contract with a private hauler for transportation.
And the city has seen increases in the cost.
Significantly through those transportation costs as well as disposal costs.
So that's very common.
As we see capacity and land fill is going down in the region.
That the cost per time at the gate would increase and the transportation costs as well.
70 miles is quite a long way to take that waste.
So the city offerings have been down on.
We've worked for a number of local governments across the nation.
And on tons of hundreds of studies.
So I'll always consider the plans, facility analyses.
To look at what could be options to make improvements to your existing facility.
It can be a new transportation or develop a landfill.
We looked at two different scenarios for a new landfill.
One would be a minimum tonnage scenario.
So that is take to me.
Sorry.
As the city.
Plus what could be expected from some of the other
Transversations within the region.
And then a maximum tonnage scenario.
So if you were to really market that material or market the capacity.
Get additional tonnage coming through.
What facility would look like with a larger landfill.
The larger the landfill oftentimes.
You know, the lower the cost.
Just based on some of those large capital improvement costs.
We looked at waste projections again for the new transportation.
Who's based on the world.
materials was both at the region and taking in the
consideration some of the other regional facilities that are existing.
So with this conversation, TUNISH looked at population
for within the area, but there's not a lot of projected
population for currently or hasn't been here recently, but you
have seen increases in your TUNISH still.
And so to be conservative, we wanted to maintain that
estimated increase year over year that you've occurred in the last
few years for your TUNISH.
So we use that to be conservative, your gate fees, so how much it costs for
folks to drop out of the conversation is low for the region.
But if you invest significant amounts of money for a new
transfer station, that rate could go up and could push waste other
places to cheaper facilities. So just to note that that
could be something that can't guarantee that TUNISH until you look at what
at the costs are within the region.
And that transportation and disposal costs would still be with a third
party and could potentially will increase over time as
landfill capacity decreases within the region.
So looking at transportation design and cost assumptions,
looks at a capacity of 25,700 tons per year, so a slight
increase over time, 0.47 percent.
I didn't interest rate of 3.5 percent,
amortized over 20 years.
Equipments on a lower five-year
amortization, looking at a five-acre property, so using
property that the city party has a transportation on.
So it would be a new development on that site.
10,000 square foot building and put a contingency on that, which is
consistency for our cost or consistent for our cost estimates.
And we didn't include revenues, so it didn't include that,
but you are bringing in charging your residents or people
bringing in outside waste as a part of this assessment.
So you're looking around $7 million in capital costs,
and that is for developing a new transportation facility,
and purchasing equipment for the transfer station.
This assumes that you would purchase a new equipment,
because we're not familiar with how old the input we have on site currently is,
but it used to be, you know,
refreshes every few years, and then regular operations and maintenance costs,
we looked over that 20-year time frame, and it comes out to be $93.27.
Well, $93.27 per ton, if you were to develop a new
transfer station to replace the existing facility.
Again, there may be opportunities to reduce that up front capital,
or use any of the equipment.
that you already have on site, but that was that analysis.
For the landfill, we looked at within a 30 mile
radius around the city.
And there are seven transfer stations, including yours.
Look to some of those transfer stations that currently
fall a significant distance similar to you all.
You'll call 70 miles.
What are the benefit with those transfer stations
have to bring in ways to a new landfill here
within this area, rather than going to some
of the other facilities?
We looked at ownership of facilities and assets.
So for example, if transfer station is owned
by a private waste entity, they would likely
take their waste through their landfill, even though it's further
away because they can do that at a lower cost versus there
were a number of transfer stations that were city owned,
or by private entities that don't have landfills,
that would be more likely to be divided to a landfill here.
Look to historical tonnage data and projections
based on the population growth of the eight county region,
because there is a larger waste shed
that can be considered for a landfill.
And we did minimum and maximum capture rates,
which I'll over here in a couple slides,
just trying to be conservative on what those tonnages could look at.
And this analysis that we've provided now
assumes that the city would take full capital cost,
full ownership and operation of this new landfill
facility, and there are some options for alternatives with that.
The minimum and maximum scenario tonnage scenarios,
the minimum was based on assuming that 20% to 50%
of the waste could be directed from other transfer stations
that were owned by cities to this area.
And then none of the waste would be divided
from any of the privately owned transfer stations.
The maximum tonnage assumed a 100% of the waste
that would be currently generated
at those transfer stations owned by cities would come to this new landfill,
as well as some of the private waste that this may be a closer proximity for them.
So that's why we ran two different scenarios,
just to try to show projections,
again, if the city decided to move forward,
there would be more discussions to really hone in on what that could look like long term.
But that gave us a facility footprint acre of 250 to 300 acres,
which is conservative.
That's not all area that would be developed into an actual landfill.
The landfill footprint is much less closer to 30 acres,
but you need a lot of area for borrow space,
storm water ponds, leachade ponds, hall roads, scale houses,
equipment building, which is a lot of other
theancillary features that are on landfills that require that.
That's it.
Similar design and cost assumptions, 3.5% interest rate over 20 years, equivalent at 5 years, assumed a cost per acre based on recent land value sales in Ottawa County. Again, no actual property or location was used for this study, so it was really just looking at if there was land available of this size within proximity.
We assumed sell development every 5 years, so when you develop a landfill, you initially develop your scale house, your buildings, your ponds, and initial sell, and then every 5 years you will develop another area or open a new area and close the old areas.
So, developing a new sell every 5 years, similar contingency, and then significant increase in staffing and equipment to account for this increase in your operation. Again, this included no revenue, so no house additional outside revenue generated by that gate tipping fees. So you would be able to set whatever rate you wanted, that you could charge to outside haulers bringing in waste.
So total here for the minimum landfill alternative, it's about 11.9 million, but over 20 years, a cost per time is 69, and 75 cents.
Not as including that new landfill capital, a new sell development, equipment, again new equipment, all being purchased and then increased operations and maintenance. And then for the larger capacity, landfill facility for the larger ten-inch.
A total of about 18 million, and that comes out to be $49.94 for ten. So as you can see, it comes much more cost effective to have a landfill when you have a lot larger waste shed or capacity of that landfill.
So in summary, your current system, your annual throughput, 19,000 tons per year, as of 2023, and the cost per ten is $77.45, looking at a new transportation and increasing the tonnage to project out some growth within the next 20 years.
We get $93.27 minimum landfill tonnage, $69.75, and then that maximum $49.94.
How long are considerations and recommendations and recommendations?
The minimum permitting design and construction timeline of a new transportation is three to five years, while the minimum equivalent for a landfill is five to seven years.
I've been permitting designing, constructing landfills for 15 years, both here in O'Homme, Kim.
Missouri. DQ has been good to work with, but there is time that is required to do
hydrogeologic investigations and making sure that your site is really suitable for
that use and then planning and permitting and design of that facility. So it's a long-term
process. Transfersation is much shorter, just based on the potential impacts and the size of
the property, it's a much different permitting process. This could be expedited. I think three to five
years is probably the minimum if you are wanting to be aggressive. They do require the state
does require at least a year of groundwater monitoring and hydrogeologic data, which this region
has quite a bit already readily available. Conducting a more thorough review of available
properties to determine cost impacts and sighting study to determine regulatory and environmental
feasibility. So the landfill costs look great, but it's all determined on viability of having a
property that makes sense. Having land that is suitable enough in size and in nature
of the state and the EPA have site location restrictions that say what is a suitable site? Let's say
proximity to groundwater, zoning, other properties, flood plains, wetlands, all of those are considerations
as well as some operational things as it close to a highway or other residences. So that would
be one of the priority next steps that have been part of that potential cost for that property purchase.
Costs are highly dependent on the quantity of waste accepted. So you would want to continue
conversations. We've talked to different transfer stations on what their thoughts were bringing waste
this direction to a new landfill, but continue that to get permit commitments to better size that
for facility and look how far out you can project that waste generation. Typically when we site land
fields we're looking at sighting them for 50, 80, 100 years of capacity because the investment for that
permitting is so significant. Evaluate transportation and landfill gate fees and landfill capacity within
the region. So again, that land that capacity goes down, that goes gate fees will go up for everyone.
It's also good to look at right now your transportation. I looked very briefly is very competitively
price with others, but as you are making investments that price may go up in need of a waste elsewhere
and then consider partnerships to support the development of a new transportation or landfill to share
in a front capital cost and provide costability long term. So we work with a lot of our local
government clients that may partner with other entities so that could be partnering with other
local communities, other tribal, tribal agency with a private waste company that could then share
in that upfront cost or could share in the burden of operations. Whether that's operational costs or
actually, we have some clients that they will pay to develop the facility and a private
waste company operates that facility on their behalf. In turn, the client that has a very
long-term, stable cost for waste management moving forward while not taking on
something that they may not be as familiar with in their data data operations. So there's a lot
of opportunities for a partnership that the city could evaluate if you wanted to move forward with
developing more infrastructure. Thank you, I'll take any questions. So you've done this. You're
pretty familiar with these operations. Yes. And do you have you worked with both the transfer
station scenario and landfill scenario? Yes. So what's your your personal preference? I mean,
what do you think is most, I guess the biggest bang for our buck? Sure. So if there are a number
of landfill facilities or processing facilities within the region, transfer stations allow
municipalities in general to have a lot of flexibility in their waste group,
where their waste can go over time, which makes other people competitive and pricing. So if you had
a lot of other options, landfills in the region where you could be, you could get really competitive
pricing and long-term stability, transfer stations are a great way to go. In areas where there isn't
a lot of other facilities, then a landfill does allow for the city to take control of their own
costs that they will have indefinitely and manage that cost to the development of a facility. And then
they can also, there is opportunities to generate revenue. I would say a lot of we work primarily
for local government clients and some of them operate landfill, some of them operate transfer stations,
some of them have both depending on how large they, how large of an operation they are. One of the
concerns that the cities have in transitioning from like a transfer station to a landfill, it is
it is a very different operation. It's a very significant operation. If you have wastewater
stream of facilities, you know, you're familiar with regulatory compliance and some of those things,
but there is sometimes a benefit to bringing a lot of partners that can help with ramping up and you
can do that even in a short-term period, whether it's a 510-year contract or longer, up to 30 years
depending on what the state or what your city and state statues allow to have someone support the
operation of that facility. So kind of really depends on what the priorities are of the city,
as well as what their comfort level is and diving into something that might be new compared to what
you are. What do you do at the transfer station?
But earlier you touched on the subject of what materials you allow to come into your landfill.
Can you expand on that a little bit?
Are you talking like medical waste and things like that?
No, so this is what was evaluated as a municipal solid waste landfill.
So this would just be your household waste.
There would be an option of construction and demolishing waste could be included as well.
So that's for construction materials that are generated.
There are opportunities if you do have enough acreage that you could even co-locate
perhaps a composting facility adjacent to that.
There might be opportunities for grant funding if you wanted to integrate something like
a composting facility.
But primarily the landfill that we evaluate with the municipal solid waste landfill, that
is the permit that would be valid for a facility like this.
So after looking at our transfer station, would you say whichever way we go, we need to be aggressive?
Yes, I would say so I personally, again, have not been to your transfer station because
I'm tagging in for someone but I have seen quite a few photos and work with a number of
transfer stations on improvement and I think that regardless, you have some work to do and quickly
would be beneficial, yes.
So again, my opinion, correct me if I'm wrong or if I'm so free jump in here as well, I feel
like we don't do we need to be aggressive, we need to be aggressive on the landfill side, otherwise
if we go to the transfer station side, we're going to have a crash problem there.
And this council, we're kind of forward thinking, and I think we can solve a long-term problem
for our community by being aggressive and going to landfill around, it may be a little more expensive
at the beginning but I think we save money in the end.
Well, you also do, well, you also do in that situation is if you were to move forward with
citing a landfill, it would prevent others from doing so likely in the region so the city would
be kind of taking that control, where if you do not decide to pursue that, there may be private
entities or others that are looking in this region to develop facilities that would be a very
affich to the city if they had a transfer station but would be out of your control.
So-
Well, how much money was talent, while making a minimum of the digital, how do I want to tell
it's a talent?
Yeah.
Except for one begins with the next one.
I just like the fact that we can control our destiny.
Yeah, true.
Then we need to.
And I think with the transfer station, we're always at someone else's mercy.
We're going to see on the cost and that cost is going to continue to go up, it's not going
to start going down.
And if we're having all of the 70 miles, gas prices are playing with that, they're fees.
We would kind of control ourselves here at least hours.
We actually make some revenue off others that want to use our way of doing so.
And, you know, other transfer stations are also hauling just as far or, you know, if not farther.
I do think that your location is a prime location for this.
I do think there are some private entities that would be interested in partnerships.
They would allow them to pull from regions that they don't.
You know, it's too far to get to their landfill, but to have something closer that they could have
either a transportation or landfill to would be very interested.
And then the city is that they control their destiny in terms of charging whatever they want at the gate.
You can negotiate different rates for different parties.
So you can still be this rate for your for your residents and for your residential and commercial collection that the city does.
And then you charge a higher rate for private waste that's brought in.
Or negotiated rates in certain quantities.
So a lot of options and flexibility there of our time.
I'm good.
Thank you.
To end.
The Greenville SEL engineering services appropriate to conduct station or substation.
Three upgrades, not to exceed 248,000, seven or forty dollars contingent.
Cloncimation of required contact document.
There.
This will be for.
And be for some three time.
I don't know.
For the protection and control.
And it's.
So before.
New control house.
Breakers.
This is.
The new.
These breakers.
This part of it.
We've had.
Thank you.
So, sir.
This.
Thank.
Open, disappears.
There's.
That.
Say.
It.
I mean.
In a.
This also includes a commissioning of any equipment after they give us a big thank you
You know, I was gonna ask
Appreciate the forward-thinking
This is just this is like Eric said this is the last
Sceptition
We have not
This is just being
Jane and far in this season. Thank you. They'll come to the Industrial Park
I mean it's like you know the design of the new Sceptation then I'm so you
Pits approved account on for a new look at that
they had it in this it's six to
Or eight to 12 weeks for
They can structure that it would be and then back to new rates that we've already seen the benefit of our infrastructure being
Upgraded, so I don't I mean this is a no brain or to me. I make a motion. I approve
I'm gonna say real quick. Thank you guys
I keep it on top right in the structure. I know Tyler had that as a focus whenever he was in your spot
Now you've moved up and kept out as a focus. I'm appreciate it
It would be business of any which is supposed to this agenda
12 staff reports
I'm Jeremy now. We're gonna make one at this later now. We need some minute. Our heat. We waste where if you're gonna plant
We did every five years. It's for the plant that we have done there by the Gulffield
We'll have a notice on the paper that if anybody gets asked about it like what it was about I mean it's for getting treated that every five years
13 trustees men in office
14 this may will be continued from counts of chamber to remain in the staff room for the purpose of executive session as
Completion of agenda item 17 of the regular meeting of the mindset again